Guide to the NYU Abu Dhabi Capstone Archives AD.MC.004
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Arts & Humanities Division Projects, 2014-2019
  - Literature and Creative Writing
    - Germaine, Carmen Caroline. Anxious Omnivores: Animal Ambivalence and Meat Ambiguity in Animals, Life of Pi, and The Year of the Flood, 2014; 2014-0011 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2014-0011)
      Abstract: This thesis examines the cultural politics and ethics of meat and meat-eating in three contemporary Canadian novels: Don LePan's Animals, 2009; Yann Martel's Life of Pi, 2001; and Margaret Atwood's The Year of the Flood, 2009. I argue that each novel contains a specific anxiety over whether—and under what conditions—eating meat is ethically justifiable, and that in each case this anxiety stems from questions about how humans draw distinctions between their own species and nonhuman animals. Each novel also demonstrates an awareness that these boundaries, both between humans and nonhumans and between different species of animals, are often arbitrary and subject to change. Fundamental human ambivalences in how to relate to different species of animals lead to the physical ambiguity of meat; acknowledging these ambivalences results in a "cannibal anxiety", or anxiety over whether eating nonhuman flesh is any different than eating human flesh. I will examine how these novels reveal or suggest ways of dealing with these ambiguities and their resultant anxieties, and how they challenge the reader to rethink both their meat-eating practices and their wider relationships to nonhuman animals in general.
      Canada; Meat; Ambiguity; Anxiety; Animals
    - James, Katherine Delia. World Literature in Spanish: Realismo Mágico from Vela to García Màrquez, 2014; 2014-0022 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2014-0022)
      Abstract: This thesis explores the forgotten history of both world literature in Spanish and the circulation of magic realism through Madrid to Latin America. By telling these oft untold stories, the thesis reevaluates current theories of world literature, as well as provides a new reading of magic realism as a genre and canonical magic realist texts such as One Hundred Years of Solitude.
      Magic realism (Literature); World literature; Core-periphery relations
    - Horst, Lauren Elizabeth. Feminism, West African Fiction, and the Problem of Genre in Buchi Emecheta's "The Rape of Shavi", 2015; 2015-0015 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2015-0015)
      Abstract: From Chinua Achebe to Buchi Emecheta, African writers have tended to write in a realist style. In creating realist narratives of resistance to colonialism and neocolonialism, these writers have implicitly cooperated with western literary critics who insist on reading literary works by African-born writers as anthropological accounts of life in "Africa." Nigerian-born author Buchi Emecheta's critical reputation was built around her early realist fiction, which critics continue to read as anthropological accounts of a universally African female experience. This paper reads Emecheta outside this critical paradigm by focusing on her only work of speculative fiction, The Rape of Shavi. Ultimately, reading Emecheta's work in relation to The Rape of Shavi suggests new modes of reading the canon of African women's fiction.
      Anthropology; Realism; Nigeria; West Africa; Feminism
    - Kelani, Naila Hafiz. On leaving a little smarter: Navigating space and a "minor" identity in transvergent post-beur cinema., 2015; 2015-0016 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2015-0016)
      Major: Literature and Creative Writing
      Abstract: Cinéma beur has traditionally been treated as a sociological cinema documenting the 'real' French-Maghrebi experience. The young protagonists of Jacques Audiard's Un Prophète (2009) and Mohamed Hamidi's Né Quelque Part (2013) navigate between Frenchness, Arabness, and Muslimness in ways that render their complex identities institutionally irreconcilable. Throughout the films' narratives, they encounter changing conceptions of their overlapping identities in the context of their movements through spaces via temporal and metaphorical journeys within (and without) the French Republic.
      Borrowing Will Higbee's notion of 'post-beur' cinema, I argue that these films resist being read through the realist, sociological, and postcolonial lenses that differentiate, if not the films themselves, then the analyses that they invite, from the "beur" generation. They mark a departure towards a transvergent cinema that deconstructs notions of center and margins, incorporating Deleuze's rhizome towards a reading of how the features and inconsistencies of a racialized French society serve as catalysts towards these characters "becoming" minoritarian.
      Algeria; France; Beur cinema; North Africa
    - Leith, Sachi. Unsettling Nomadism: Becoming-Minor in Galsan Tschinag's Die Rückkehr, 2015; 2015-0019 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2015-0019)
      Major: Literature, History
      Abstract: The study of non-ethnic German authors, of increasing importance to German literature, has traditionally focused only on those within Germany. The enigmatic work of Galsan Tschinag, however, a Tuvan Mongolian shaman and author of thirty books in German, provokes a radical re-imagination of the contours of German literary and linguistic history. His fictionalized autobiography Die Rückkehr: Roman meines Lebens [The Return: Novel of my Life], the most aesthetically self-conscious of his texts, invokes Mongol, Soviet, Tuvan, and European literary forms to weave together Central Asian and European histories. I read Die Rückkehr in conversation with Deleuze and Guattari's Toward a Minor Literature, whose emphasis on language as a deterritorialized, dynamic space of imagination, rather than an entity circumscribed by national boundaries, allows me to analyze Tschinag's work within the broader contexts of German and Mongolian literatures, and of minor literatures in general. The text's formal experimentation and staging of autobiographical truth through fiction allow the author to comment on both post-socialist Mongolia and contemporary Germany. By revealing the various traditions that converge in his work, I argue for a more integrated understanding of Eurasian history via German as a global language.
      German language; German Writing; Germany; Postsocialism; Deterritorialization; Postcolonialism; Mongolia; Shamans; Nomads; Minor literature
    - Sutherland, Jamie Alexander. 'The Time-Devouring Nightingale': Toward A Borgesian Conception of World Literature, 2015; 2015-0008 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2015-0008)
      Abstract: Many of Jorge Luis Borges's works reject linear understandings of time, allowing him to rewrite history and tradition. Borges uses translation to reshape his literary heritage, as well as his own national history. This practice is exemplified by his 1925 translation of the last page of James Joyce's Ulysses in the publication Proa, which recreates Ulysses in Buenos Aires and, when published, challenged conceptions of what Argentine literature should look like. His Antología de la literatura fantástica ('Anthology of Fantastic Literature'), which includes other translated portions of Ulysses, upsets traditional understandings of the canon, periods of literary history, and traditional practices of translation. My project explores Borges's unconventional understanding of chronology to consider how his literary texts unsettle orthodox understandings of world literature, as well as of Argentine history and literary tradition. An alternative conception of world literature based on a non-linear sense of time elucidates Borges's own works, as well as Joyce's Ulysses, and suggests how current dominant models of world literature could be reimagined.
      |a Joyce, James, |d 1882-1941. |t Ulysses; Spanish language; World literature; Argentina
    - Hu, Zoë. Disorderly Time in Jhumpa Lahiri and Amitac Ghosh: Narrative Studies as a Strategy for Reading Migration Novels., 2016; 2016-0018; This project relies on the field of narrative studies to demonstrate how migration novels by Lahiri and Ghosh espouse conceptions of migration temporalities that stray from the irreversible, often times oppressive, model of linear time. Employing concepts of narrative temporality, I argue that these texts attribute more agency to the fictional migrant and promote an optimistic sense of migration in which the homeland can be recovered from a shifting, malleable experience of time. This project thus highlights narrative form as a productive site where new conceptions of time and migration in literature can thrive and converge. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2016-0018)
      This project relies on the field of narrative studies to demonstrate how migration novels by Lahiri and Ghosh espouse conceptions of migration temporalities that stray from the irreversible, often times oppressive, model of linear time. Employing concepts of narrative temporality, I argue that these texts attribute more agency to the fictional migrant and promote an optimistic sense of migration in which the homeland can be recovered from a shifting, malleable experience of time. This project thus highlights narrative form as a productive site where new conceptions of time and migration in literature can thrive and converge.
    - ElZoghbi, Mariam. Ra7ala, 2017; 2017-0005; Ra7ala is a semi-autobiographical novella, that follows Leila, a young Egyptian woman who has recently re-discovered her Palestinian roots, as she goes to Palestine in search of her great-grandmother's house. This journey brings Leila face-to-face with her family's history and with questions about identity, loss, and diaspora. Leila's story also illustrates the nature of privilege, in that Leila is able to go on this journey with the thought that she will be able to return, and that she is able to determine for herself how she wants to be defined. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0005)
      Ra7ala is a semi-autobiographical novella, that follows Leila, a young Egyptian woman who has recently re-discovered her Palestinian roots, as she goes to Palestine in search of her great-grandmother's house. This journey brings Leila face-to-face with her family's history and with questions about identity, loss, and diaspora. Leila's story also illustrates the nature of privilege, in that Leila is able to go on this journey with the thought that she will be able to return, and that she is able to determine for herself how she wants to be defined.
    - Ulen, Grega. Angels of History: Feminist Politics of Autobiography and Historiography in Maja Haderlap's Angel of Oblivion and Assia Djebar's Fantasia: An Algerian Cavalcade., 2017; 2017-0004; Using Maja Haderlap's 2011 Angel of Oblivion and Assia Djebar's 1985 Fantasia: An Algerian Cavalcade, this paper articulates a theoretical paradigm that rethinks subjectivity and temporality in order to affirm autobiographical narratives of grief as sites of historical revisionism. Reading the novels as autobiographies reveals the transformation of forms that dissolve the individual subject and give voice to the collective heritage of silenced women. The project draws on Walter Benjamin's notion of messianic time to call attention to the ways in which the novels interrupt patriarchal and imperialist productions of history. Bringing together these feminist and postcolonial autobiographies from disparate contexts elaborates an ethics and aesthetics of individual and collective mourning practices that force us to reexamine how we think about "history." (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2017-0004)
      Using Maja Haderlap's 2011 Angel of Oblivion and Assia Djebar's 1985 Fantasia: An Algerian Cavalcade, this paper articulates a theoretical paradigm that rethinks subjectivity and temporality in order to affirm autobiographical narratives of grief as sites of historical revisionism. Reading the novels as autobiographies reveals the transformation of forms that dissolve the individual subject and give voice to the collective heritage of silenced women. The project draws on Walter Benjamin's notion of messianic time to call attention to the ways in which the novels interrupt patriarchal and imperialist productions of history. Bringing together these feminist and postcolonial autobiographies from disparate contexts elaborates an ethics and aesthetics of individual and collective mourning practices that force us to reexamine how we think about "history."
    - Al Bastaki, Shamma. بيت لبيتHouse to House, 2018; 2018-0036; House to House is a collection of ethnographic, photographic, and text-image based poetry in which I present undocumented oral narratives of the diverse peoples of the Dubai Creek, including communities of Al Bastakiya, Al Shindagha, and Deira, mostly through details of the everyday, or what George Perec termed the "infraordinary." This work explores the blurred boundaries between memory and history, and how memory, in its fragmentation, reproduction, retelling, (and un-telling), eventually becomes its own kind of history. ​ (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0036)
      House to House is a collection of ethnographic, photographic, and text-image based poetry in which I present undocumented oral narratives of the diverse peoples of the Dubai Creek, including communities of Al Bastakiya, Al Shindagha, and Deira, mostly through details of the everyday, or what George Perec termed the "infraordinary." This work explores the blurred boundaries between memory and history, and how memory, in its fragmentation, reproduction, retelling, (and un-telling), eventually becomes its own kind of history.
    - Al Kubaisi, Noor. Wesam's Sister, 2018; 2018-0032; The novella centers around questions of faith, self-discovery, and the difficulties confronting a Muslim family as it tries to preserve their Muslim identity in a Western city. This story is told from the perspective of Zahra Alim, an Iraqi-British eighteen-year-old returning to Edinburgh to clean out the dorm room of her sister, Dua, who has disappeared from college without a trace. Zahra stumbles upon a stack of letters Dua had written just before her disappearance and discovers that Dua lived a whole other life unbeknownst to her family. As she reads through the letters, Zahra faces the dilemma of whether or not to tell her parents about her sister's secret life. • My novella begins with "She looks at herself" – That is essentially what this whole project is about: self-discovery, reflection, but not only so, my novella is about looking back and understanding, empathizing and recognizing the struggles and actions of one's family – more specifically, a Muslim family in a Western society. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0032)
      The novella centers around questions of faith, self-discovery, and the difficulties confronting a Muslim family as it tries to preserve their Muslim identity in a Western city. This story is told from the perspective of Zahra Alim, an Iraqi-British eighteen-year-old returning to Edinburgh to clean out the dorm room of her sister, Dua, who has disappeared from college without a trace. Zahra stumbles upon a stack of letters Dua had written just before her disappearance and discovers that Dua lived a whole other life unbeknownst to her family. As she reads through the letters, Zahra faces the dilemma of whether or not to tell her parents about her sister's secret life. • My novella begins with "She looks at herself" – That is essentially what this whole project is about: self-discovery, reflection, but not only so, my novella is about looking back and understanding, empathizing and recognizing the struggles and actions of one's family – more specifically, a Muslim family in a Western society.
    - Flores, Gabrielle. Tayeb Salih's Season of Migration to the North Across Its Intertexts, 2018; 2018-0032; This capstone studies the intertextual relationships within Tayeb Salih's Season of Migration to the North. As a postcolonial narrative, the novel straddles Eastern and Western literary traditions and uses these literary references to strategically resist any one reading. Intertextuality becomes a game under the hand of the novel: it is cognizant of the global literary landscape that it must participate in, with these various literary references becoming a performative exercise in striking the balance between disparate influences and cultures that a postcolonial novel comes out of. Gérard Genette's classification of transtextuality has been useful in understanding how different modes of intertextuality can work within the same space. Aamir Mufti's conception of World Literature highlights the cultural dynamics that underlie such references. Thinking with both highlights the need to re-evaluate how intertextuality fits within these new literary contexts. Season of Migration to the North seems to be anticipating space for a kind of postcolonial intertextuality, which owes a debt to theories of intertextuality while highlighting how such a technique becomes a strategic tool for a novel to insert itself into a universal library. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0028)
      This capstone studies the intertextual relationships within Tayeb Salih's Season of Migration to the North. As a postcolonial narrative, the novel straddles Eastern and Western literary traditions and uses these literary references to strategically resist any one reading. Intertextuality becomes a game under the hand of the novel: it is cognizant of the global literary landscape that it must participate in, with these various literary references becoming a performative exercise in striking the balance between disparate influences and cultures that a postcolonial novel comes out of. Gérard Genette's classification of transtextuality has been useful in understanding how different modes of intertextuality can work within the same space. Aamir Mufti's conception of World Literature highlights the cultural dynamics that underlie such references. Thinking with both highlights the need to re-evaluate how intertextuality fits within these new literary contexts. Season of Migration to the North seems to be anticipating space for a kind of postcolonial intertextuality, which owes a debt to theories of intertextuality while highlighting how such a technique becomes a strategic tool for a novel to insert itself into a universal library.
    - Jayatilake, Thirangie. The Difficulties of Resistance: The Female Body as object in The Lament of the Dhobi Woman, The End of Innocence, and Fasting, Feasting., 2018; 2018-0030; The paper explores the difficulty of resisting the patriarchy in three South Asian novels, The Lament of Dhobi Woman, The End of Innocence and Fasting, Feasting. The young female characters in the novels use their bodies as tools for resisting the patriarchy. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0030)
      The paper explores the difficulty of resisting the patriarchy in three South Asian novels, The Lament of Dhobi Woman, The End of Innocence and Fasting, Feasting. The young female characters in the novels use their bodies as tools for resisting the patriarchy.
    - Kawas, Vivi. Writing as a Case of Performative Translation: A Reading of Valeria Luiselli's Fiction and Non-Fiction, 2018; 2018-0035; This Capstone Project is an analysis of the fiction and non-fiction works of Mexican contemporary writer, Valeria Luiselli. This analysis seeks to conceptualize "performative translation" as a new term that refers broadly to the ways in which translation is built into the form and content of a text in its "original" iteration. The project operates on an understanding of translation as a creative practice. Finally, in proposing this new concept, the project emphasizes the relevance of Luiselli's work in introducing academic and non-academic works that encourage a rethinking of translation's capaciousness as an analytical concept and creative strategy for writing. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0035)
      This Capstone Project is an analysis of the fiction and non-fiction works of Mexican contemporary writer, Valeria Luiselli. This analysis seeks to conceptualize "performative translation" as a new term that refers broadly to the ways in which translation is built into the form and content of a text in its "original" iteration. The project operates on an understanding of translation as a creative practice. Finally, in proposing this new concept, the project emphasizes the relevance of Luiselli's work in introducing academic and non-academic works that encourage a rethinking of translation's capaciousness as an analytical concept and creative strategy for writing.
    - Memon, Mashal. Dear Nani Amma, 2018; 2018-0008; Dear Nani Amma is a novella that explores the issues of diasporic death, the concept of home and the silences and absences that unfold in the life of a Pakistani family after a family member passes away. It centers around Safiya, a twelve-year-old girl, as she tries to grapple with the new family dynamics. She must take on a caretaker position, while at the same time dealing with her own anxieties being bullied at school. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0008)
      Dear Nani Amma is a novella that explores the issues of diasporic death, the concept of home and the silences and absences that unfold in the life of a Pakistani family after a family member passes away. It centers around Safiya, a twelve-year-old girl, as she tries to grapple with the new family dynamics. She must take on a caretaker position, while at the same time dealing with her own anxieties being bullied at school.
    - Nielsen, Nikolaj. Erasure as Resistance: HOMO Sapienne in/as Contemporary Greenlandic Literature, 2018; 2018-0011; I propose that through a radical contextualization of HOMO Sapienne—which considers the literary historical trajectory into which the novel inserts itself, the rhetorical disparagement of contemporary Greenlanders by their historical colonizers, and the market-facing considerations Korneliussen and her publisher might make to slate the novel for wider circulation among those former colonizers—we discover a unique rhetorical strategy in HOMO Sapienne that other postcolonial may emulate to maximize their readership without mollifying the potential anger of or discontent in their texts: Rather than verbalize any anger she may feel with Greenland's pre-post-colonial wounding by its former colonizers, Korneliussen writes Denmark out of existence, provincializing the former colonizing country and using erasure and non-representation not just to sublimate HOMO Sapienne's anger, but to amplify poignancy and impact. (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2018-0011)
      I propose that through a radical contextualization of HOMO Sapienne—which considers the literary historical trajectory into which the novel inserts itself, the rhetorical disparagement of contemporary Greenlanders by their historical colonizers, and the market-facing considerations Korneliussen and her publisher might make to slate the novel for wider circulation among those former colonizers—we discover a unique rhetorical strategy in HOMO Sapienne that other postcolonial may emulate to maximize their readership without mollifying the potential anger of or discontent in their texts: Rather than verbalize any anger she may feel with Greenland's pre-post-colonial wounding by its former colonizers, Korneliussen writes Denmark out of existence, provincializing the former colonizing country and using erasure and non-representation not just to sublimate HOMO Sapienne's anger, but to amplify poignancy and impact.